Mia Birdsong: Why is Black Lives Matter important for the US right now
ميا بيردسونغ: لماذا حركة (حياة السود مهمة) مهمة الآن بالنسبة لأمريكا
and in the world?
وفي العالم؟
Patrisse Cullors: Black Lives Matter is our call to action.
باتريس كولورز: (حياة السود مهمة) هي دعوة إلى العمل.
It is a tool to reimagine a world
هي وسيلة لإعادة تخيل عالم
where black people are free to exist,
حيث الناس السود يملكون حرية الوجود،
free to live.
وحرية العيش.
It is a tool for our allies to show up differently for us.
هي وسيلة لحلفائنا ليُظهروا دعمهم لنا بوسائل مختلفة.
I grew up in a neighborhood that was heavily policed.
لقد نشأت في حي تسوده رقابة أمنية شديدة.
I witnessed my brothers and my siblings
شهدت أخي وأقربائي
continuously stopped and frisked by law enforcement.
أثناء توقيفهم وتفتيشهم المستمرين من قبل السلطات.
I remember my home being raided.
أتذكر مداهمة منزلي .
And one of my questions as a child was, why?
وكانت أحد أسئلتي حينما كنت طفلة : لماذا؟
Why us?
لماذا نحن؟
Black Lives Matter offers answers to the why.
هذه الحركة توفر الجواب عن هذه الأسئلة.
It offers a new vision for young black girls around the world
إنها توفر رؤية جديدة للفتيات السود في أنحاء العالم
that we deserve to be fought for,
مفادها أننا نستحق أن يُدافع عنا،
that we deserve to call on local governments to show up for us.
وأننا نستحق أن نستدعي السلطات المحلية ليدافعوا عنا.
Opal Tometi: And antiblack racism --
أوبال توميتي: والعنصرية ضد السود --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And antiblack racism is not only happening in the United States.
والعنصرية ضد السود لا تحدث فقط في أمريكا .
It's actually happening all across the globe.
إنها في الحقيقة تحدث عبر العالم أجمع.
And what we need now more than ever is a human rights movement
وما نحتاجه الآن أكثر من أي وقت مضى هو حركة حقوق الإنسان
that challenges systemic racism in every single context.
التي تتحدى العنصرية المنظمة بكل وجوه أشكالها.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We need this because the global reality
نحن بحاجة لهذا لأن الواقع العالمي
is that black people are subject to all sorts of disparities
هو أن الناس السود يخضعون لجميع أوجه المفارقات
in most of our most challenging issues of our day.
في أغلب مشاكلنا وأكثرها تحديًا في يومنا الحالي.
I think about issues like climate change,
أفكر بمشاكل كـ التغيير المناخي
and how six of the 10 worst impacted nations by climate change
وكيف أن ستة من 10 دول تأثرت بشكل سيء من جراء التغيير المناخ
are actually on the continent of Africa.
في الواقع هم في قارة أفريقيا.
People are reeling from all sorts of unnatural disasters,
الناس تترنح من كل أنواع الكوارث الغير طبيعية
displacing them from their ancestral homes
تنتزعهم من مواطن أجدادهم
and leaving them without a chance at making a decent living.
وتتركهم بلا أي فرصة لصنع حياة كريمة.
We also see disasters like Hurricane Matthew,
نحن نرى أيضًا كوارث كإعصار ماثيو،
which recently wreaked havoc in many different nations,
الذي عاث خرابًا في الآونة الأخيرة في العديد من الدول المختلفة،
but caused the most damage to Haiti.
ولكن سبب الضرر الأكبر لهاييتي.
Haiti is the poorest country in this hemisphere,
هاييتي البلد الأفقر في هذا الوسط،
and its inhabitants are black people.
وسكانها من الناس السود.
And what we're seeing in Haiti
وما نراه في هاييتي
is that they were actually facing a number of challenges
هو أن الناس يواجهون الكثير من التحديات
that even preceded this hurricane.
التي تسبق هذا الإعصار حتى.
They were reeling from the earthquake,
كانوا يترنحون من الزلزال،
they were reeling from cholera that was brought in by UN peacekeepers
ويترنحون من الكوليرا التي أتت من قبل صانعي سلام الأمم المتحدة
and still hasn't been eradicated.
وما تزال لم يتم القضاء عليها.
This is unconscionable.
هذا غير معقول.
And this would not happen if this nation didn't have a population that was black,
هذا لم يكن ليحدث لو لم يكن سكان هذه الأمة من السود،
and we have to be real about that.
ولنكن صريحين بهذا الأمر،
But what's most heartening right now
ولكن أكثر ما يشجع الآن
is that despite these challenges,
بالرغم من هذه التحديات
what we're seeing is that there's a network of Africans
التي نشاهدها، أنه هناك شبكة من الأفارقة
all across the continent
عبر القارة بأكملها
who are rising up and fighting back and demanding climate justice.
ينهضون ويدافعون ويطالبون بالعدالة المناخية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
MB: So Alicia,
حسنًا أليشا،
you've said that when black people are free,
لقد قلتي عندما يكون السود أحرارًا،
everyone is free.
الجميع سيكون حر.
Can you talk about what that means?
هل تستطيعين التحدث عم تقصدينه؟
Alicia Garza: Sure.
أليشا غارزا: بالطبع.
So I think race and racism is probably the most studied
حسنًا أعتقد بأن العرق والعنصرية من المحتمل أكثر الظواهر
social, economic and political phenomenon in this country,
الاجتماعية، الاقتصادية، والسياسية دراسة في هذا البلد،
but it's also the least understood.
ولكن مع هذا الأقل فهمًا.
The reality is that race in the United States
الواقع بأن العرق في الولايات المتحدة
operates on a spectrum from black to white.
يتدرج علي مقياس من الأسود للأبيض.
Doesn't mean that people who are in between don't experience racism,
وهذا لا يعني بأن الناس الذين يكونون في الوسط لا يعانون العنصرية،
but it means that the closer you are to white on that spectrum,
ولكن هذا يعني أنه كل ما أصبحت قريب من الأبيض
the better off you are.
كل ما كان أفضل لك.
And the closer to black that you are on that spectrum
والأقرب للسواد
the worse off your are.
الأسوء لك.
When we think about how we address problems in this country,
عندما نفكر كيف نوصف مشكلاتنا في هذا البلد،
we often start from a place of trickle-down justice.
نحن غالبًا ما نبدأ من مكان تدريجي للعدالة
So using white folks as the control we say,
لهذا نستخدم أشخاص بيض في السلطة
well, if we make things better for white folks
حسنًا إذا جعلنا الأمور أفضل لأصحابنا البيض
then everybody else is going to get free.
الجميع حينها سيكونون أحرار.
But actually it doesn't work that way.
ولكن في الحقيقة هذا الأمر لا يتم هكذا.
We have to address problems at the root,
نحن بحاجة لنعرف المشاكل من جذورها،
and when you deal with what's happening in black communities,
وعندما تتعامل مع ما يحدث في مجتمعات السود
it creates an effervescence, right?
هذا يخلق فوران صحيح؟
So a bubble up rather than a trickle down.
يتزايد عوضًا عن أن ينقص تدريجيًا.
Let me give an example.
دعوني أعطي مثال
When we talk about the wage gap,
عندما نتكلم عن فارق المرتبات،
we often say women make 78 cents to every dollar that a man makes.
غالبًا نقول النساء تأخذن 78 سنت لكل واحد دولار يأخذه الرجال.
You all have heard that before.
كلنا سمعنا ذلك من قبل،
But those are the statistics for white women and white men.
ولكن هذه الإحصائيات للنساء البيض والرجال البيض.
The reality is that black women make something like 64 cents
في الواقع النساء السود يأخذن 64 سنت
to every 78 cents that white women make.
لكل 78 سنت تأخذه النساء البيض.
When we talk about latinas, it goes down to about 58 cents.
عندما نتكلم عن اللاتينيات فأنه يهبط إلى 58 سنت
If we were to talk about indigenous women,
عندما نتكلم عن نساء الشعوب الأصلية
if we were to talk about trans women,
عندما نتكلم عن النساء المتحولات جنسيًا
it would even go further down.
عندها ينخفض أكثر.
So again,
حسنًا مجددًا
if you deal with those who are the most impacted,
إذا كنت تتعامل مع الذين هم أكثر تأثرًا
everybody has an opportunity to benefit from that,
الجميع لديه فرصة ليستفيد من ذلك،
rather than dealing with the folks who are not as impacted,
عوضًا عن التعامل مع أولئك الذين لا يتأثرون،
and expecting it to trickle down.
ونتوقع حينها أن ينخفض.
MB: So I love the effervescence,
لهذا أحب الفوران،
bubbling up.
الفقاقيع.
AG: Effervescence -- like champagne.
الفوران كالشمبانيا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
MB: Who doesn't love a glass of champagne, right?
من لا يحب كأس من الشمبانيا، صحيح؟
Champagne and freedom, right?
الشمبانيا والحرية، صحيح؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
What more could we want, y'all?
ماذا عسانا أن نريد أكثر، جميعنا؟
So you all have been doing this for a minute,
إذًا جميعكم كنتم تفعلون هذا لدقيقة،
and the last few years have been --
والسنين القليلة الماضية كانت--
well, I can't even imagine,
حسنًا لا أستطيع أن أتخيل،
but I'm sure very transformative.
ولكن أنا متأكدة كثيرة التغيير.
And I know that you all have learned a lot about leadership.
وأعلم بأنكم جميعًا تعلمتم الكثير عن القيادة.
What do you want to share with these people
ماذا ستشاركون مع هؤلاء الناس
about what you've learned about leadership?
حول ما تعلمتم عن القيادة؟
Patrisse, let's start with you.
باتريس لنبدأ معك.
PC: Yeah, we have to invest in black leadership.
نعم يجب علينا أن نستثمر في قيادة السود.
That's what I've learned the most in the last few years.
هذا ما تعلمته في السنين القليلة الماضية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
What we've seen is thousands of black people showing up for our lives
ما رأيناه كان آلاف الناس السود دعمونا لأرواحنا
with very little infrastructure and very little support.
مع بنية تحتية ضعيفة ودعم قليل.
I think our work as movement leaders isn't just about our own visibility
أعتقد عملنا كقادة حركة لايقتصر على رؤيتنا
but rather how do we make the whole visible.
ولكن كيف لنا أن نجعلها مرئية.
How do we not just fight for our individual selves
كيف لنا ألا ندافع فقط عن أنفسنا كأفراد
but fight for everybody?
ولكن أن نقاتل من أجل الجميع؟
And I also think
وأعتقد أيضًا
leadership looks like everybody in this audience
القيادة تبدو كل شخص في هذا الحضور
showing up for black lives.
يدعم حياة السود.
It's not just about coming and watching people on a stage, right?
أنه ليس فقط الحضور ومشاهدة الناس على المنصة، صحيح؟
It's about how do you become that leader --
أنه كيف تصبح هذا القائد--
whether it's in your workplace, whether it's in your home --
سواء كان في مكان عملك، أو كان في منزلك--
and believe that the movement for black lives isn't just for us,
وتؤمن بأن حركة حياة السود ليس لنا فقط.
but it's for everybody.
ولكنها للجميع.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
MB: What about you, Opal?
ماذا عنكِ أوبال؟
OT: So I've been learning a great deal about interdependence.
حسنًا كنت قد تعلمت الكثير عن الترابط
I've been learning about how to trust your team.
تعلمت كيف تثق بفريقك.
I've come up with this new mantra
وجدت هذا الشعار الجديد
after coming back from a three-month sabbatical,
بعد عودتي من إجازة التفرغ العلمي لثلاث شهور،
which is rare for black women to take who are in leadership,
وهو من النادر أن تأخذه النساء السود اللواتي هن في القيادة،
but I felt it was really important for my leadership and for my team
ولكن شعرت أنه لمن المهم لي ولفريقي
to also practice stepping back
بأن نتدرب على التراجع قليلاً
as well as also sometimes stepping in.
كما يجب أحيانًا أن نبادر.
And what I learned in this process was that we need to acknowledge
وكان ما تعلمته في هذه العملية بأننا بحاجة أن نعرف
that different people contribute different strengths,
أن أُناس مختلفون يُساهمون بقدرات مختلفة،
and that in order for our entire team to flourish,
وليزدهر فريقنا بأكلمه
we have to allow them to share and allow them to shine.
يجب علينا أن نسمح لهم بأن يُشاركوا، نسمح لهم أن يتألقوا.
And so during my sabbatical
وخلال إجازتي
with the organization that I also work with,
من المؤسسة التي كنت أعمل معها،
I saw our team rise up in my absence.
رأيت فريقي ينهض في غيابي.
They were able to launch new programs,
كانوا قادرين أن يبدأوا برامج جديدة،
fundraise.
جمع تبرعات.
And when I came back,
وعندما عدت،
I had to give them a lot of gratitude and praise
كان علي أن أعطيهم الكثير من الامتنان والمدح
because they showed me that they truly had my back
لأنهم أظهروا لي أنهم حق العون
and that they truly had their own backs.
وهم حقًا حق العون لأنفسهم.
You know, in this process of my sabbatical,
أتعلمي في خلال إجازتي
I was really reminded
تذكرت حقًا
of this Southern African philosophy of Ubuntu.
فلسفة جنوب أفريقية هي أوبونتو.
I am because you are;
أنا لأني أنت؛
you are because I am.
أنت لأني أنا.
And I realized that my own leadership,
ولاحظت بأن قيادتي
and the contributions that I'm able to make,
والمساهمة التي كنت قادرة على فعلها
is in large part due to the contributions that they make, right?
في جزء كبير منها هي بسبب إسهاماتهم التي يفعلوها، صحيح؟
And I have to acknowledge that, and I have to see that,
وعلي أن أعترف بذلك وأراه،
and so my new mantra is, "Keep calm and trust the team."
إذًا شعاري الجديد هو "ابق هادئًا وثق في فريقك"
And also,
وأيضًا،
"Keep calm and thank the team."
"ابق هادئًا واشكر فريقك"
MB: You know, one of the things I feel like I've heard
أتعلمون، من الأشياء التي قد سمعت بها
in the context of the Black Lives Matter movement more than anywhere else
في مفهوم حركة حياة السود مهمة أكثر من أي مكان أخر
is about being a leaderful movement,
هو كونها حركة قيادية،
and that's such a beautiful concept,
وهذا مفهوم جميل حقًا،
and I think that something
وأعتقد بأن
that women often bring to the conversation about leadership
ما جلبته هؤلاء النسوة للحوار عن القيادة
is really the collective piece.
هو عمل جماعي مشترك.
What about you, Alicia?
ماذا عنكِ أليشا؟
AG: Yeah ...
حسنًا...
How many of you heard that saying that leadership is lonely?
كم منكم قد سمع بأن القيادة كونك وحيدًا؟
I think that there is an element where leadership is lonely,
أعتقد بأن هنالك عامل حيث تكون القيادة كونك وحيدًا،
but I also believe that it doesn't have to be like that.
ولكن أنا أعتقد أيضًا بأنها لا يجب عليها أن تكون كذلك.
And in order for us to get to that point,
ولكي نتمكن من الوصول إلى تلك النقطة،
I think there's a few things that we need to be doing.
أعتقد بأن هناك أمور عدة يجب علينا فعلها
So one is we have to stop treating leaders like superheroes.
إذًا أولاً يجب علينا أن نتوقف عن معاملة القادة كأبطال خارقون.
We are ordinary people attempting to do extraordinary things,
نحن بشر عاديون، نحاول أن نفعل أمور غير عادية،
and so we need to be supported in that way.
لهذا نحتاج أن نتلقى دعم بهذه الطريقة.
The other thing that I've learned about leadership
الشيء الآخر الذي قد تعلمته عن القيادة
is that there's a difference between leadership and celebrities, right?
بأن هناك اختلاف بين القيادة والشهرة، صحيح؟
And there's a way in which we've been kind of transformed into celebrities
وهناك طريقة ما تحولنا خلالها إلى مشاهير
rather than people who are trying to solve a problem.
عوضًا عن أُناس يحاولون أن يحلوا المشكلة.
And the way that we treat celebrities is very fickle, right?
والطريقة التي نعامل بها المشاهير متقلبة جدًا، صحيح؟
We like them one day,
نحبهم يوم،
we don't like what they're wearing the next day,
لا يعجبنا ما يرتدونه في اليوم التالي،
and all of a sudden we have issues, right?
وفجأة يصبح لدينا مشاكل صحيح؟
So we need to stop deifying leaders
إذًا يجب علينا أن نتوقف عن تأليه القادة
so that more people will step into leadership.
ليخطو أكبر عدد من الناس نحو القيادة.
Lots of people are terrified to step into leadership
الكثير من الناس لديهم حالة رعب من التقدم نحو القيادة
because of how much scrutiny they receive
بسبب مقدار المراقبة الذي يتلقونه
and how brutal we are with leaders.
وكم نحن وحشيون مع القادة.
And then the last thing that I've learned about leadership
وآخر شيء تعلمته حول القيادة
is that it's really easy to be a leader when everybody likes you.
أنه من السهل جدًا أن تكون قائدًا عندما يحبك الكل
But it's hard to be a leader when you have to make hard choices
ولكن إنه لمن الصعب أن تكون كذلك عندما يتوجب عليك أخذ قرار صعب
and when you have to do what's right,
وعندما يتوجب عليك أن تقوم بما هو صائب،
even though people are not going to like you for it.
حتى لو لم يحبك الناس بعد ذلك
And so in that way,
وفي هذه الحالة إذًا
I think another way that we can support leaders
أعتقد بإمكاننا أن ندعم القادة بطريقة أُخرى
is to struggle with us,
بأن يكافحوا معنا،
but struggle with us politically,
ولكن يكافحوا معنا سياسيًا،
not personally.
وليس شخصيًا.
We can have disagreements without being disagreeable,
يمكننا ألا نتفق بدون خلافات بيننا
but it's important for us to sharpen each other,
ولكن من المهم أن نشحذ بعضنا البعض،
so that we all can rise.
وبهذا ننهض جميعنا.
MB: That's beautiful, thank you.
هذا جميل، شكرًا لك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So you all are doing work
إذًا جميعكم تقومون بعمل
that forces you to face some brutal, painful realities
يجبركم أن تواجهوا بعض الوحشية ووقائع مؤلمة
on a daily basis.
بشكل يومي.
What gives you hope
ما الذي يعطيكم أمل
and inspires you in that context?
وما يلهمكم في هذا المضمون؟
PC: I am hopeful for black futures.
يحدوني الأمل لمستقبل حياة السود.
And I say that because we live in a society
وأقول هذا لأننا نعيش في مجتمع
that's so obsessed with black death.
مهووس بموت السود،
We have images of our death on the TV screen,
لدينا صور قتلانا على التلفاز
on our Twitter timelines,
وعلى التويتر،
on our Facebook timelines,
وعلى صفحات الفيسبوك،
but what if instead we imagine black life?
ولكن ماذا لو عوضًا عن تصور حياة السود
We imagine black people living and thriving.
نتصور الناس السود يعيشون ويزدهرون
And that --
وهذا--
that inspires me.
هذا ما يلهمني.
OT: What inspires me these days are immigrants.
ما يلهمني هذه الأيام هم المهاجرون
Immigrants all over the world who are doing the best that they can
مهاجرون حول العالم يفعلون أفضل ما يوسعهم
to make a living, to survive and also to thrive.
ليحظوا بحياة، لينجحو وليزدهروا.
Right now there are over 244 million people
الآن هناك أكثر من 244 مليون شخص
who aren't living in their country of origin.
لا يعيشون في بلدهم الأصلي.
This is a 40 percent increase since the year 2000.
هذه زيادة 40% عن عام 2000
So what this tells me
إذًا ما الذي يعنيه هذا
is that the disparities across the globe are only getting worse.
أن الفوارق في جميع أنحاء العالم تزداد سوءًا.
Yet there are people who are finding the strength and wherewithal to travel,
ومع هذا لايزال هناك ناس يجدون القوة والوسائل الكافية للسفر،
to move,
للانتقال،
to eke out a better living for themselves
يحتالون على حياة أفضل لأنفسهم
and to provide for their families and their loved ones.
لإعالة عائلاتهم وأحبائهم.
And some of these people who are immigrants
وبعض هؤلاء الناس الذين هم مهاجرون
are also undocumented.
ليسوا موثقين.
They're unauthorized.
هم غير مصرح بهم.
And they inspire me even more
وهم يلهمونني أكثر
because although our society is telling them, you're not wanted,
لأنه على الرغم من أن مجتمعنا يقول لهم بأنهم غير مرغوب بهم
you're not needed here,
وليس لهم حاجة هنا،
and they're highly vulnerable and subject to abuse, to wage theft,
وليس لهم قيمة وموضع للإساءة وسرقة الأجور،
to exploitation and xenophobic attacks,
للاستغلال وهجمات كارهي الأجانب،
many of them are also beginning to organize in their communities.
العديد منهم بدأوا بتنظيم أنفسهم في مجتمعاتهم.
And what I'm seeing is that there's also an emerging network
وما أراه هو بأن هناك أيضًا شبكة للاندماج
of black, undocumented people who are resisting the framework,
السود، الغير موثقين، الذين يقاومون التأطير
and resisting the criminalization of their existence.
ويقاومون تجريم وجودهم.
And that to me is incredibly powerful
هذا بالنسبة لي قوي للغاية
and inspires me every singe day.
ويلهمني في كل يوم.
MB: Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
Alicia?
أليشا؟
AG: So we know that young people are the present and the future,
إذن نعلم بأن الصغار هم الحاضر والمستقبل،
but what inspires me are older people
ولكن ما يلهمني هم كبار السن
who are becoming transformed in the service of this movement.
الذين تحولوا لخدمة هذه الحركة.
We all know that as you get older,
نحن نعلم بأنه عندما نكبر،
you get a little more entrenched in your ways.
تتشبث أكثر بطرقك الخاصة.
It's happening to me, I know that's right.
هذا يحدث لي، أنا أعلم بأن هذا صحيح
But I'm so inspired when I see people who have a way that they do things,
ولكن يلهمني كثيرًا عندما أرى ناس لديهم طريقة بفعل الأشياء،
have a way that they think about the world,
لديهم طريقة ليفكروا بالعالم،
and they're courageous enough to be open to listening to what the experiences are
وهم شجعان كفاية ليكونوا منفتحين ليسمعوا لخبرات
of so many of us who want to live in world that's just
العديد منا، الذين يريدون أن يعيشوا في عالم عادل
and want to live in a world that's equitable.
يريدون أن يعيشوا في عالم منصف.
And I'm also inspired by the actions that I'm seeing older people taking
ويلهمني أيضًا الأفعال التي يقومون بها
in service of this movement.
في خدمة هذه الحركة.
I'm inspired by seeing older people step into their own power and leadership
يلهمني أن أرى كبار السن يتقدمون بقوتهم وقيادتهم
and say, "I'm not passing a torch,
ويقولون "أنا لا أمرر المشعل،
I'm helping you light the fire."
بل سأساعدكم بإشعال النور."
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
MB: I love that --
أحببت هذا--
yes.
نعم.
So in terms of action,
إذًا من حيث المبادرة
I think that it is awesome to sit here and be able to listen to you all,
أعتقد أنه أمر رائع أن أجلس هنا وأكون قادرة علي الاستماع إليكم جميعًا
and to have our minds open and shift,
بعقل مفتوح قابل للتغيير،
but that's not going to get black people free.
ولكن هذا لن يجعل الناس السود أحرار،
So if you had one thing you would like this audience
إذًاَ، إذا كان لديكم شيء واحد من الجمهور
and the folks who are watching around the world to actually do,
وأصحابنا الذين يشاهدون حول العالم ليفعلوه حقًا
what would that be?
ماذا سيكون؟
AG: OK, two quick ones.
حسنًا، شيئان سريعان
One, call the White House.
أولاً، اتصلوا بالبيت الأبيض
The water protectors are being forcibly removed
حماة المياه يطاح بهم بالقوة
from the camp that they have set up to defend what keeps us alive.
من الخيم التي بنوها ليدافعوا عما يبقينا أحياء.
And that is intricately related to black lives.
وهذا مربوط بصورة معقدة بحياة السود.
So definitely call the White House and demand that they stop doing that.
لذا بالتأكيد اتصلوا بالبيت الأبيض وطالبوهم بالتوقف عن فعل ذلك.
There are tanks
هناك دبابات،
and police officers arresting every single person there as we speak.
وضباط شرطة يعتقلون كل شخص هناك ريثما نتكلم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The second thing that you can do
الشيء الثاني الذي بإمكانكم فعله
is to join something.
هو الانضمام لشيء ما.
Be a part of something.
كونوا جزء من شيء ما
There are groups, collectives --
هناك مجموعات، تعاونيات--
doesn't have to be a non-profit, you know what I mean?
ليس من المهم أن تكون غير ربحية، تفهمون ما أقصد؟
But there are groups that are doing work in our communities right now
ولكن هناك مجموعات تقوم بالعمل في مجتمعاتنا الآن
to make sure that black lives matter so all lives matter.
ليُأكدوا بأن حياة السود مهمة إذًا كل الأرواح مهمة.
Get involved;
انضموا لهم؛
don't sit on your couch and tell people what you think they should be doing.
لاتجلسوا علي أريكتكم وتخبروا الناس ما يتوجب عليهم فعله.
Go do it with us.
انهضوا وافعلوه معنا.
MB: Do you guys want to add anything?
هل تريدون أن تضيفوا شيئًا يا رفاق؟
That's good? All right. So --
هذا جيد؟ حسنًا --
And I think that the joining something,
أعتقد بأن الانضمام لشيء ما،
like if you feel like there's not something where you are, start it.
حتى عندما تشعر أنه لا يوجد شيء حيث أنت، أبدأه.
AG: Start it.
أبدأه.
MB: These conversations that we're having,
هذه الحوارات التي نقوم بها
have those conversations with somebody else.
قوموا بتلك المحادثات مع شخص آخر
And then instead of just letting it be a talk that you had,
ومن ثم عوضًا عن أن يكون مجرد حوار قمتم به
actually decide to start something.
في الحقيقة قرروا أن تبدأوا بشيء ما.
OT: That's right.
هذا صحيح.
MB: I mean, that's what you all did.
أقصد هذا ما نقوم به جميعًا
You started something, and look what's happened.
بدأتم بشيء والآن انظروا ماذا حدث.
Thank you all so much for being here with us today.
شكرًا لكم جميعًا لحضوركم معنا اليوم.
OT: Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)